A Guide to the Richmond (Va.) Judgments, 1788-1950 (bulk 1890-1950)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Richmond (Va.) Judgments, 1788-1950 (bulk 1890-1950)
Library of Virginia
50.7 cubic feet (113 boxes); 60 volumes.
Richmond (Va.) Hustings Court; Richmond (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Judgments, 1798-1866, relating to free and enslaved Black and multiracial individuals are digitized and available through Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection on the Library of Virginia website. Please use digital images.
Acquisition Information
Portions of these records came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Richmond City in 1968 under accession 26922 and in 2019 under accession 52743.
Remainder of records came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from Richmond City in an undated accession.
Historical Information
Context for Record Type: Judgments are identified as civil suits, often involving debt, heard by a jury on the "law" side of the court as opposed to the "chancery" (or equity) side. Should the defendant not have funds to repay the debt, the court ordered their property (including enslaved people) to be seized and sold to repay the debt owed to the plaintiff. Judgments also contain suits brought by enslaved people seeking to gain their freedom.
In Judgments, an assumpsit or declaration (sometimes referred to as a narratio) lays out the plaintiff's grievance as a petition acted as a formal application to the court requesting judicial action. Judgment suits also generally included record types like subpoenas, summons, and exhibit. Judgments may also include additional documentations such as executions, bonds, and various kinds of writs.
Judgment suits make up a large quantity of a locality's records; consequently, they provide a great deal of information concerning the activities and interests of the people who lived in the locality. Since the vast majority of judgment suits relate to financial matters, they are a valuable resource in studying the economic and social history of Virginia localities and are the impotence for many chancery suits.
Types of Courts: Richmond (Va.) Hustings court created by the General Assembly in 1782 at the time Richmond was granted it's charter. The court was created to handle all criminal cases, civil law cases, probate of wills, fiduciary accounts, deed recordings, all licenses (business, marriage, etc.), citizenship applications, etc. It also included the Mayor's Court.
Richmond (Va.) Circuit Court created in 1852 as a successor to the Circuit Court of Chancery for the County of Henrico in order to handle all civil and criminal matters, same as other circuit courts for counties, cities, or towns. In July 1954, the Clerk of Law and Equity Court was named clerk of the Circuit Court. At the same time, it's jurisdiction was limited to criminal proceedings against convicts in the penitentiary, proceeding to enforce payment of money to commonwealth and suits against public officers representing the commonwealth.
Locality History Note: The city of Richmond, located between Henrico and Chesterfield Counties, was named by William Byrd (1674-1744), who envisioned the development of a city at the falls of the James River and with the help of William Mayo laid out the town in 1737. The name probably came from the English borough of Richmond upon Thames, which Byrd visited on several occasions. Richmond was established in 1742 and in 1779 was designated the capital of Virginia effective 30 April 1780. It was incorporated as a town, although "stiled the city of Richmond," in 1782 and was incorporated as a city in 1842. It served as the capital of the Confederacy from mid-1861 to April 1865. Richmond was enlarged by the annexation of Manchester (or South Richmond) in 1910, and by the addition of Barton Heights, Fairmount, and Highland Park in 1914. Further annexations from Chesterfield County occurred in 1942 and 1970.
Lost Locality Note: During the burning of Richmond on April 3, 1865, during the Civil War, Richmond circuit court judge John A. Meredith led efforts to save the circuit court records found at the State Court House. Rescuers successfully removed all the papers that were necessary to pending suits and many of the order books, but all of the wills and deed books were lost. Records of the superior court and circuit superior court of law and chancery were also destroyed. Most of the pre-Civil War Hustings Court records exist.
Scope and Content
Richmond (Va.) Judgments, 1788-1950, consist of civil cases in which justice was administered on the strictly formulated rules of common law. The majority of the cases in this record group relate to matters of debt. There are additional judgments located in the unprocessed Richmond (Va.) Ended Causes. Identified judgement records include: Judgments, 1798-1866, relating to free and enslaved Black and multiracial individuals; Judgments, 1788-1949; Office Judgments, 1806-1905; and Judgment Dockets and Indexes, 1833-1950.
Judgments, 1798-1866, relating to free and enslaved Black and multiracial individuals consists of one box of judgements. Many of these suits pertain to debts and disputes regarding the sale and hire of enslaved Black individuals by white residents. Other disputes include issues with apprenticeships, self-emancipating Black and multiracial person, and conflicts in proving legal status.
Judgments, 1788-1949, consists of unprocessed law cases.
Office Judgments, 1806-1905, consists of unprocessed law cases ruled on by a judge outside of a traditional hearing.
Judgment Dockets and Indexes, 1833-1950, are volumes that help provide identifying information for law cases. These may contain the date, names of the plaintiff, and names of the defendants.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Judgments, 1798-1866, relating to free and enslaved Black and multiracial individuals
Series II: Judgments, 1788-1949
Series III: Office Judgments, 1806-1905
Series IV: Judgment Dockets and Indexes, 1833-1950
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also:Richmond (Va.) Ended Causes, 1782-1951 (bulk 1900-1951) for additional judgments unprocessed
Records related to free and enslaved people of Richmond (Va.) and other localities are available through the Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection on the Library of Virginia website.
Additional Richmond (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Richmond City is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Richmond City Court Records may be found in the Lost Records Localities Digital Collection on the Library of Virginia website.
Contents List
- Judgments relating to free and enslaved Black and multiracial individuals, 1798-1866, .23 cubic feet (1 box)
  Loosely arranged chronologically.
  - Judgments 1798-1866
- Judgments, 1788-1949, 25.7 cubic feet (57 boxes)
  - Title Dates Covered
  - Judgments by Confession & Dismissions at Rules 1867
  - Judgments by Confession & Dismissions at Rules 1867
  - Judgments 1875
  - Judgments 1876
  - Judgments 1894
  - Judgments 1895
  - Judgments 1896
  - Judgments 1897
  - Judgments 1925
  - Judgments 1926
  - Judgments 1927
  - Judgments 1928
  - Judgments 1929
  - Judgments 1930
  - Judgments 1931
  - Judgments 1932
  - Judgments 1933
  - Judgments 1934
  - Judgments 1939
  - Judgments 1944
  - Judgments 1945
  - Judgments 1946
  - Judgments 1947
  - Rules and Judgments 1788-1799
  - Judgments 1837-1860
  - Ended Causes: Judgments, Dismissions, Schedules 1842-1843; 1853; 1856
  - Ended Causes: Judgments, Dismissions, Schedules 1844, 1856, 1857
  - Judgments 1860-1871
  - Common Law Cases; Habeas Corpus Cases; Grand Jury Summons; Misc. Common Law; Judgments from Hustings Court 1860-1880 circa
  - Judgments 1871-1874
  - Judgments 1877-1879
  - Judgments 1880-1884
  - Judgments 1885-1888
  - Judgments and Office Judgments 1887-1888
  - Judgments 1888-1889
  - Judgments 1889-1890
  - Judgments 1890-1891
  - Judgments 1892-1893
  - Judgments 1898-1899
  - Judgments 1900-1903
  - Judgments from Manchester (Va.) Police Court 1900-1912 circa
  - Judgments from Manchester (Va.) Police Court 1903-1907 circa
  - Judgments 1904-1907
  - Notices of Motions for Judgments; M 1904-1914
  - Judgments 1908-1911
  - Judgments 1912-1914
  - Judgments 1915-1917
  - Judgments 1918-1922
  - Judgments 1923-1924
  - Judgments 1935-1936
  - Judgments 1937-1938
  - Judgments 1940-1941
  - Judgments 1942-1943
  - Judgments 1948 Aug-Dec
  - Judgments 1948 Jan-July
  - Judgments 1949 Jan-June
  - Judgments 1949 July-Oct
- Office Judgments, 11806-1905, 24.8 cubic feet (55 boxes); 2 volumes
  - Office Judgments, 1823; Ended Cause 1823
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments 1837
  - Office Judgments & Dismissions 1840
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments 1860
  - Office Judgments 1867
  - Office Judgments 1870
  - Office Judgments 1872
  - Office Judgments 1874
  - Office Judgments 1875
  - Office Judgments 1876
  - Office Judgments 1877
  - Office Judgments 1878
  - Office Judgments 1880
  - Office Judgments 1889
  - Office Judgments 1890
  - Office Judgments 1891
  - Office Judgments 1892
  - Office Judgments 1893
  - Office Judgments 1894
  - Office Judgments 1895
  - Office Judgments 1896
  - Ended Causes; Dismissions at Rules; Office Judgments 1806-1807
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments; Abatements and Dismissions at Rules 1807-1808
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments 1808 May-1809 Mar
  - Ended Causes; Dismissions; Office Judgments; Recognizance Bonds 1808-1813 Nov
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments 1809 Mar-Dec
  - Ended Causes; Dismissions; Office Judgments 1809-1811 Sep
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments 1810 Mar-Nov
  - Ended Causes; Dismissions; Office Judgments 1813 Nov-1814 Aug
  - Ended Causes; Dismissions at Rules; Office Judgments 1815 March-1816 Nov
  - Ended Causes; Dismissions; Office Judgments 1816 Aug-1817 May
  - Ended Causes; Dismissions; Office Judgments 1816 Nov-1818 Mar
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments 1818 Aug-1819 Apr
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments; Dismissions 1818 Jan-Aug
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments; Dismissions 1819 May-Aug
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments; Dismissions 1820 Aug-1821 Feb
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments; Dismissions 1820 May-Aug
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments 1828-1829
  - Office Judgments 1829-1832; Dismissions at Rule 1829-1831; Recognizances 1829-1832
  - Dismissions at Rule 1832, 1833, 1834; Office Judgments 1833, 1834, 1835; Schedules 1837-1840; Recognizances 1832, 1833 1832-1835
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments; Dismissions; Recongnizances 1835-1839; Ended Causes, 1839 Nov-Dec
  - Office Judgments; Dismissions 1838-1839
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments; Dismissions 1840-1841
  - Ended Causes; Office Judgments 1860-1861
  - Vacation Orders and Office Judgment 1861-1868
  - Office Judgments 1865-1866
  - Office Judgments 1867-1868
  - Office Judgments (1868) & Subpoenas 1868-1915
  - Office Judgments (1869) & Subpoenas 1869-1917
  - Office Judgments 1872-1873
  - Office Judgments 1881-1882
  - Office Judgments 1883-1884
  - Office Judgments 1885-1886
  - Office Judgments 1892-1893
  - Office Judgment Book 1894-1949
  - Office Judgments 1897-1901
  - Office Judgments 1902-1905
- Judgment Dockets and Indexes, 1833-1950, 58 volumes
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1884
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1916
  - Judgment Docket 1833-1838
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1838-69
  - Judgment Docket 1842-1869
  - Judgment Docket 1855-1858
  - Judgment Docket 1858-1869
  - Index to Judgments 1858-67
  - Judgment Docket 1869-1870
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1869-70
  - Judgment Docket 1870-1875
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1870-75
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1873-74
  - Judgment Docket 1874-84
  - Judgment Docket 1875-1878
  - Judgment Docket Book 1875-1885
  - Judgment Index Sheets [not verified 1875-1910
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1875-78
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1878-84
  - Index to Judgments [in Defendants' 1878-96
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1884-88
  - Judgment Docket 1884-97
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1888-90
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1890-93
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1893-96
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1896-98
  - Judgment Docket 1897-1915
  - Index to Judgments [in Defendants' 1897-1917
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1898-1903
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1904-10
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1910-16
  - Judgment Docket 1915-17
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1917-22
  - Judgment Lien Docket and Execution 1917-26
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1922-25
  - General Index to Judgments 1925-1954
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1925-26
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1926-27
  - Judgment Lien Docket and Execution 1926-30
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1927-29
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1929-31
  - Judgment Lien Docket and Execution 1930-40
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1931-32
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1932-34
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1934-36
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1936-38
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1938-41
  - Judgment Lien Docket and Execution 1940-48
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1941-44
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1944-46
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1945-48
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1946-48
  - Judgment Lien Docket 1948-49
  - Judgment Lien Docket and Execution 1948-49
  - Judgment Lien Docket and Execution 1949-50
  - General Index to Judgment Liens, De undated
  - General Index to Judgment Liens, De undated
  - Index to Judgment Docket No. 12 undated